<section id="chapter1">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Reef uses the AMQP (<ulink url="http://www.amqp.org"/>) for transport and Google Protocol Buffers (<ulink
            url="http://code.google.com/p/protobuf/"/>) to serialize messages. The combination of these two technologies
        comprise the interface to the Reef service layer. Bindings can be created for any platform/language with a
        compatible AMQP client and a Protobuf compiler. Reef is factored as a RESTful service oriented architecture
        (SOA).
    </para>

    <figure id="AMQP_Broker">
        <title>Client, broker, services interaction</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/protos.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Since Reef runs on the JVM, the reference implementation for the client binding is written for Java. The
        client API handles details of maintaining a connection to an AMQP broker, routing service requests to their
        named AMQP exchanges, providing the asynchronous delivery of service message events, and building the proper
        request headers.
    </para>
    <para>
        For the user, the client API involves the management of two central objects: <emphasis>Connection</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Session</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Connection</emphasis>: Maintains a connection to the AMQP broker, handles the threading
                    of asynchronous communication, acts as a Session factory. The underlying implementation extends the
                    <literal>IConnection</literal>
                    interface.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Session</emphasis>: Used by a single thread at a time, provides methods for making
                    service requests. Users interact with the
                    <literal>ISession</literal>
                    interface.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        Implementations of
        <literal>IConnection</literal>
        must be thread-safe, but
        <literal>ISession</literal>
        must be used by only one thread at a time. The AMQP protocol itself fully allows for multiple concurrent
        sessions.
    </para>

    <figure id="Session_threading">
        <title>Threading of IConnection and ISession</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/thread2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
        <literal>ISession</literal>
        interfaces represent long-lived objects that are associated one-to-one with underlying AMQP sessions.

      Because there is a small cost associated with acquiring a new session, it is not recommended to use a new session per request.
      However, users should feel free to create as many sessions as needed to service their threading requirements. Recommended practice
      for multi-threaded applications is therefore to create an <literal>ISession</literal> per <emphasis>unit of concurrency</emphasis>,
      rather than synchronizing on a single session instance.</para>
      <para>Some users, especially those writing server applications, may want to pool <literal>ISession</literal> instances in order to
      increase performance. In these cases, care must be taken to ensure the correct authorization is attached before any given request.</para>
</section>
