<section id="model_entities">
    <title>Modeling in Reef</title>
    <para>
        The SCADA portion of Reef is primarily concerned with providing operators and applications a view at the
        current state of the real world system and allow issuing of commands to affect that system. To understand the
        how and why of the parts of the Reef system it is first important to understand how a very simple real world
        system would be modeled. We are using a simplified power distribution model for these examples but the modeling
        is flexible enough to handle all common SCADA applications.
    </para>
    <para>
        Below is a simplified representation of an electrical circuit breaker with an attached power
        line. In this simplified system we are pretending that the circuit breaker has two status points indicating if
        it is currently Closed or Tripped (open) and two commands Trip and Close that will cause it to change state. We
        are
        modeling the power line to have two analog points, Voltage and Current, that indicate how much power is flowing
        through the line.
    </para>
    <figure id="model_example">
        <title>Simple "Real World" System</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/model_example.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <section id="logical_model">
        <title>Logical Model</title>
        <para>
            It makes sense to arrange these points based on which piece of equipment they are most closely associated
            with.
            In the Reef system we call this the "logical model." In power systems it is common to consider points and
            commands to be "owned" by pieces of equipment which may be themselves owned by "equipment groups".
        </para>
        <figure id="equipment_hierachy">
            <title>Logical Model</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/equipment_hierachy.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <remark>Annotate substation w/ equipment group, Line and Breaker with eqipument</remark>
        </figure>
        <para>
            In Reef we model this logical tree by assigning every object an "Entity" node that describes the name and
            type (ex: Point, Command, Equipment, etc) of the object. So for the proceding example we create entities for
            four points, two commands, two pieces of equipment and one equipment group. We then create an edge with type
            "owned" from the equipment group to both pieces of equipment. From each piece of equipment we create an edge
            to the points and commands they own. Notice these edges are directed, we would say "Line1 owns voltage" or
            "voltage is owned by Line1"; "voltage owns Line1" would imply the opposite relationship.
        </para>
        <figure id="equipment_tree_1">
            <title>Logical Model as Entities</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/equipment_tree.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <remark>Remove point "power"</remark>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="communication_model">
        <title>Communication Model</title>
        <para>
            The "logical model" describes the system in "domain specific" terms.
            In most domains the logical units we model are not themselves "intelligent electronic
            devices" (IEDs) we can collect data from. For example the logical entity "power line" is not actually a box
            we can plug an ethernet cable into and have it report the voltage and current passing through it, it is
            simply a copper wire.
            In the real world we generally only have a limited set of telemetery on a system often collecting
            measurements for many logical pieces of equipment using a single piece of equipment (IED).

            In the case of a power line we may have attached transducers for current and voltage that are being sampled
            by a relay.
            Below is one possible layout for how we would measure the points in our simple substation example.
        </para>
        <figure id="comms_model_example">
            <title>Instrumentation of Real World</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/comms_model_example.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <remark>indicate transducers and command points, possibly with indexes</remark>
        </figure>
        <para>
            We model an IED as a "communication endpoint" which is responsible for points and commands. A "sourcefor"
            edge is added from the endpoint to each of points and commands.

            We use this relationship to update the online flag on points and commands and provide visualizations for
            engineers to help them diagnose communication failures.
        </para>
        <figure id="partial_communication_tree">
            <title>Communication Tree</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/communication_tree.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <remark>Remove port and config file.</remark>
        </figure>
        <para>
            Communication Endpoints  are the equipment in the real world that Reef will be communicating with using
            field protocols like DNP3, Modbus or ICCP.

            Many of these field protocols require complex configuration parameters to specify the specifics of how to
            configure the protocol and the exact format of the returned data and how to map that data to the
            measurements we are creating, we put this sort of data in ConfigFiles that the protocol adapter
            can pull out of the services.

            We also need to know the address of the equipment, whether that is an TCP/IP address or a serial
            port name and location.

            Each of these pieces of information is also assigned an Entity and an edge of "uses" is
            added from the communication endpoint to each of those entities.
        </para>

        <figure id="full_communication_tree">
            <title>Communication Tree</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/communication_tree.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
            While it is true that some pieces of field equipment are "smart" and would be modeled as both a piece of
            equipment and as a communication endpoint; modeling them seperately leads to a much easier to understand
            system for all users.

            An operator or application needs to only concern itself with the "logical model" without having to know how
            the data is actually being collected.

            If an operator is troubleshooting a communication issue they can look soley
            at the communication model and ignore the logical model.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="aggregate_model">
        <title>Aggregate Model</title>
        <para>
            All of the points and commands are used in both the communication and logical models and this explains why
            we gave each of the models a relationship type ("owns" and "sourcefor").

            Each point or command will have an edge pointing to logical owner and its communication endpoint.

            When we merge the two trees we end up with a single pool of entities that may be related to one or many
            other entities.

            In computer science this is called a "directed graph with colored edges" and forms the basis of the entity system.
        </para>
        <figure id="combined_tree">
            <title>Merged Tree</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/combined_tree.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
            Applications and HMIs will use these relationships to determine the "shape" of the system, the entities
            themseleves do not contain any "type specific" information specific to each type of entity.

            Some examples of "type specific" information are "is this command blocked", "is this communication endpoint
            considered online" or "is this point currently marked abnormal".

            This data is represented in Reef with the type specific messages (sometimes refered to as concrete types)
            like Point or Command.

            Applications will generally want to use the "concrete types" because they contain the interesting data,
            they will use the entity system to determine the UUIDs for the concrete objects they are using.
        </para>
        <figure id="entities_plus_abstract">
            <title>Entities vs. Concrete Types</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/entities_plus_abstract.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
</section>